AGUSTIN GUERRA

304-871-1833 | agustinguerra@ufl.edu | LinkedIn | Website

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

I am a highly motivated engineering professional with **+5** years of experience in the transportation industry and **+4** years of research experience in traffic engineering. My research interest includes optimization algorithms considering Connected and Automated Vehicles (CAVs) capabilities, operations research, machine learning applications, real-time implementation of CAVs, traffic flow theory, microsimulation, human factors, and driving simulator studies. Currently, my PhD dissertation focuses on developing optimization algorithms for **real-time** applications considering CAVs in urban arterials. The algorithms are developed and simulated in **Python** considering the joint optimization of vehicles' trajectories and Signal Phasing and Timing (SPaT).

EDUCATION

PhD, Civil Engineering University of Florida Dissertation: Optimization of Traffic Performance in Signalized Arterials with CAVs	Aug. 2019 – May 2023 Gainesville, FL
MS, Civil Engineering University of Kansas Thesis: Modeling Discretionary Lane Change in a Connected Environment	Aug. 2017 – May 2019 <i>Lawrence, KS</i>
BS, Civil Engineering Universidad Tecnologica de Panama	Mar. 2008 – May 2013 <i>Panama, PA</i>

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant Aug. 2019 – Present

University of Florida

- Performed all phases of the research process, including problem definition, literature review, research design, data collection, analysis of results, and preparation of reports
- Developed optimization algorithms in Python to improve traffic performance on signalized arterials considering CAVs capabilities
- Assisted in the implementation of optimization algorithm for isolated intersections
- Facilitated the coordination of projects activities to meet deadlines
- Formulated different optimization models to reduce intersection delays, including LP, IP, and MILP models
- Developed heuristic methods using search-based algorithms to reduce delays in arterials
- Developed a Python-based data pipeline to extract trajectories from connected vehicles
- Implemented various techniques for data preprocessing, including data normalization, outlier detection and removal, and feature selection, to ensure the quality and integrity of the data prior to analysis
- · Evaluated machine learning algorithms to estimate the occurrence of future crashes

May. 2018 – May. 2019

University of Kansas

1 of 4

- Conducted a driving simulator study to assess human behavior during Discretionary Lane-Changing (DLC) maneuvers under connected environments
- Implemented a predictive DLC fuzzy logic model in a driving simulator

Updated: April 12, 2023

• Optimization modeling (LP, MIP, heuristic search), Python (Matplotlib, CPLEX, Gurobi, Numpy, Pandas, SciPy, scikit-learn, TensorFlow), signal control/traffic flow theory, human-factors, driving simulator, data pipelines, data scrapping, project management, research methodology & design, participant recruitment, data collection, data management, data analysis, R, SPSS, ETEX, oral presentations, Education and Public Outreach (EPO)

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-Reviewed Journals

[1] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefeteriadou. Platooning Trajectory Optimization for Connected Automated Vehicles in Coordinated-Arterials. *Transportation Research Record*, 2022

Conference Proceedings

[1] L. Carvalho, **Guerra, A.**, X. Wang, P. Manjunatha, L. Elefteriadou. Simulation Platform for Testing and Evaluation of CAV Trajectory Optimization and Signal Control Algorithm Integrated with Commercial Traffic Simulator. *Proceedings of the 2022 Winter Simulation Conference*

Under Preparation

- [1] **Guerra, A.**, E. Amini, L. Elefeteriadou. A Computationally-Efficient Algorithm to Enable Joint Optimization of Connected Automated Vehicles' Trajectories and Signal Phasing and Timing in Coordinated Arterials, 2023
- [2] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefeteriadou. Analysis of Trajectory Control Strategies for Connected Automated Vehicles in a Comercial Microsimulator, 2023
- [3] **Guerra, A.**, M. Asgharzadeh, A. Kondyli. Modeling Driving Behavior during Discretionary Lane Change in a Connected Environment, 2023

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant

Sep. 2020 - Dec. 2020

University of Florida

- Developed and taught three graduate lectures for the traffic flow theory course
- Explained and assisted students with traffic flow theory assignments
- Created reference material (example problems) to help students understand key concepts, including the motion of single vehicles, car-following models, shock-wave analysis, flow regimes, and capacity
- Educated students on deficiencies of existing signal control strategies, such as detection, communication delay, and computation time
- Introduced CAVs concepts, discrete optimization methods, Python-programming language as a tool for developing optimization frameworks for CAVs
- Developed reference material for PhD students about Python, version control (git, and github), and discrete optimization

2 of 4 Updated: April 12, 2023

PRESENTATIONS

- [1] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefteriadou. Optimizing Signalized Coordinated Arterial Performance in a Fully Automated Environment. A Heuristic Approach. *The Transportation Research Board (TRB) 102st Annual Meeting*, 2023
- [2] **Guerra, A.**, L. Salas-Nino. Actuated Micromobility Users Presence Awareness System in Urban Arterials. *The Transportation Research Board (TRB) 102st Annual Meeting*, 2023
- [3] **Guerra, A.**, V. Zorbas, L. Elefeteriadou. In a Hurry? Try Going Slower. *Florida Automated Vehicle (FAV)*Summit, 2022
- [4] Elefteriadou, L., Amini, E., Carvalho, L., **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefteriadou. Leveraging CAVs to Improve Traffic Operational Quality. *T3e Webinar: Impacts on Roads from Automated Driving System (ADAS) ITS Professional Capacity Building Program*, 2022
- [5] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefteriadou. A Trajectory-based Method for Platoon Formation of Connected and Automated Vehicles. *7th Annual UTC Conference for the Southeastern Region*, 2022
- [6] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefeteriadou. Platooning Trajectory Optimization for Connected Automated Vehicles in Coordinated-Arterials. *The Transportation Research Board (TRB) 101st Annual Meeting*, 2022
- [7] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefeteriadou. Platooning Trajectory and Signal Phasing Optimization for Connected Automated Vehicles in Coordinated-Arterials. *The Transportation Research Board (TRB) 101st Annual Meeting*, 2022
- [8] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefeteriadou. Computation Efficient Alternative for Connected Automated Vehicles Platoon Formation. *Florida Automated Vehicle (FAV) Summit*, 2021
- [9] **Guerra, A.**, M. Asgharzadeh, A. Kondyli. Discretionary Lane Changing Decisions for Connected-Vehicles Based on Fuzzy Logic. *Transportation Research Board* 99th Annual Meeting Transportation Research Board, 2020

TECHNICAL REPORTS

[1] Manjunatha P., L. Elefteriadou, M. Hunter, H. Zhou, S. Noei, **A. Guerra**, L. Carvalho, R. Favero, A. Guin, A. Saroj. Evaluation of Advanced Vehicle and Communication Technologies through Traffic Microsimulation (Project I5) *Phase II, Task 1*, 2022 (ongoing project)

LEADERSHIP/INVOLVEMENT

Founding Member and Chair of the IEEE-ITSS Student Chapter : Led the efforts to establish an IEEE Student Chapter branch of the ITSS at the University of Florida	2021 – 2022
ITE University Chapter Vice President: Coordinated student seminars and ITE activities	2021 – 2022
Student Representative at the UFTI Internal Steering <u>Committee</u> : Promoted engagement activities between industry professionals and students	2020 – 2022
Media Manager at KU Fulbright Student <u>Association</u> : Led dissemination of activities promoted by the Fulbright Student Board, 2018	2018 – 2019

3 of 4 Updated: April 12, 2023

FELLOWSHIPS & AWARDS

•	 Anne Brewer Academic Scholarships: Awarded by the Intelligent Transportation Society (<u>ITS</u>) Florida Chapter 	2022
•	• Second Place, IEEE-ITSS Logo Design Competition: Awarded by the IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Society (<u>ITSS</u>)	2022
•	Fulbright Fellowship: Awarded by the U.S Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs to complete a Master's Degree at the University of Kansas	2017
•	• Global Best Project in Roads and Highways : Awarded by the <u>ENR</u> for the Coastal Beltway project in Panama	2015
•	• Petroterminal of Panama Scholarship : Awarded by the Petroterminal of Panama (PTP) to complete a Bachelors's Degree at the Universidad Tecnologica de Panama	2009

PROFESSIONAL SOCIETIES

IEEE: Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers	2022 – Present
TRB AME40: TRB Standing Committee on Transportation in Developing Countries	2022 – Present
IEEE-ITSS: IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Society	2022 – Present
ITE: Institute of Transportation Engineers	2019 – Present
ASCE: American Society of Civil Engineers	2021 – 2022

INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

Highway & Traffic Consultant

May 2019 - Aug. 2019

Panama

- Provided safety assessment for roadways, interchanges, and intersections
- Developed geometric design proposals for transportation infrastructure projects
- Conducted earthwork estimation for highway projects

Highway Engineer

Nov. 2012 – Aug. 2017

Panama

Louis Berger

WSP

• Developed geometric designs for proposal and as-built drawings for highway projects with a project portfolio comprising several projects in the Latin American region (Panama, Colombia, Honduras, and Peru) totaling \$3 billion in construction amount

- Coordinated with different departments (geotechnical, hydraulic, and pavement) to meet deadlines
- Created digital model terrain for highway projects
- Verified slope stability analysis using the Slide-Rockscience software
- Supervised and provided mentorship to a team of four drafters, contributing to their professional development and ensuring project deliverables met quality standards

REFERENCES

Lily Elefteriadou, PhD: Barbara Goldsby Professor, University of Florida elefter@ce.ufl.edu **Alexandra Kondyli, PhD**: Associate Professor, University of Kansas akondyli@ku.edu **Juliana Canas**: Senior Advisor, First Climate juliana.canas-vanegas@firstclimate.com

4 of 4 Updated: April 12, 2023